I teach a couple of courses that talk
significantly about wisdom one of them
is a course on higher cognitive
processes so I'm going to try and
collapse all of that information into a
ten minute talk about the nature of
wisdom so wisdom involves some
transformation of our cognition that
affords an improvement of our lives it
helps to reduce foolishness and helps to
afford flourishing it frees us from ways
in which our cognition is working
against itself and frees us to improve
the way our cognition can work with
itself that means that wisdom has to do
with some central or fundamental
function of our cognition and one of the
things that I've argued in my work
elsewhere is one of the central
functions of our cognition what really
affords our ability to learn and to
solve problems is our ability to realize
relevance to zero in on relevant
information and ignore irrelevant
information this seems to be what is
really constitutive of us being
intelligent agents so intelligence is
basically your capacity for learning and
relevance realization can be thought
initially as just our ability to zero in
on information find patterns and thereby
learn about the world but the problem is
that relevance realization process has
to be self-correcting it has to be self
transcending because the patterns we
find can often prevent us from solving
the problems we face so here's a classic
example of this it's called the nine dot
problem it's a very famous problem very
studied in psychology so here's the
problem you have to join all nine dots
with four straight lines and you have to
start the previous line sorry you have
to start the next line from the terminus
of the previous line so what many people
do is they immediately project a pattern
onto here
the that's their intelligence at work
they project a square and they think of
it that what I have to do is create a
closed figure and so they try and solve
the nine dots they draw four lines oh I
missed the center they do this sent oh
this isn't working and then it turns out
to be very difficult so here's one
solution to the nine dot problem one two
three four right lines now what's
important there is when you do this many
people say you cheated or you that's not
fair you went outside the box but
exactly that's the issue I at no point
said Square or box that was a pattern
that your intelligence imposed on there
that was the way you realized relevance
you said this is relevant and all this
space outside isn't relevant but it
turns out the space outside is relevant
and what your relevance realization what
your intelligence has to do is transcend
itself incorrect itself it has to
feedback on itself and so what you have
to do is not only learn fine pattern you
have to pay attention to how you're
finding patterns you have to do not only
learning you have to do learning to
learn what that means is one of the
things your intelligence can do is
actually feedback on itself and do
learning to learn now when you can do
that when you're learning to learn helps
you overcome how you've missed framed a
problem we call that insight and what I
want to suggest to you is that insight
is one of the central functions of
wisdom look if I say Bob doesn't have a
lot of knowledge but he's very wise
people say yeah that's okay that makes
sense or if you say you know Bob is very
creative but he's not very wise people
go yeah that's okay but if I say to you
Bob is very wise but he's not very
insightful people go know that that
doesn't work that doesn't make any sense
so insight is a central capacity to
being wise now the thing about insight
in wisdom is we're not just talking
about you know improving how to solve a
particular problem we're talking about
again this comprehensive improvement of
our cognition of our intelligence
because we're trying to afford reducing
foolishness foolishness is being trapped
by our own cognition like you're trapped
in the nine problem flourishing is when
you do this right when intelligence
feeds on itself and we do learning to
learn when you afford your mind to be
able to work better than it was working
before but we want to do this
comprehensively now what I want to
suggest to you is that when intelligence
is insightfully
getting back on itself so that we get
learning to learn that's actually what
rationality is intelligence is using
your intelligence to solve the problem
through learning to learn of how to
better use and develop your intelligence
that's what rationality is and
rationality I think is therefore a key
element of what it is to be wise now the
problem that many people have when they
hear the word rationality is they
misunderstand it they think of it as
being logical kind of the you know the
spark or data thing from or you know the
Star Trek popular culture thing but I
want to suggest to you that it's much
more sophisticated than that so just
like the way intelligence can feedback
on itself to make it make us rational
what I want to suggest to you is the way
rationality can feedback on itself
transcend itself correct itself overcome
its self limitation afford its self
improvement that's what we mean by
wisdom now in order to talk about that
we have to talk about the three types of
knowing the three kinds of patterns that
our intelligence projects into the world
now the one we're very familiar with are
patterns that that we express in
propositions like I know that that
Australia is a continent I know that
Australia is a country I know that
Australia is a continent and the country
right and there what we need is we need
to improve our inferential abilities the
problem with our inferential abilities
is they're often beset by biases we jump
to conclusions we don't pay attention to
possibilities we don't properly consider
the relevant information that is going
into our inference but what we need to
do is develop a set of skills called by
Jonathan Barron active open mindedness
where we learn to find these biases and
we learned to correct them so what's an
example of a bias often when people are
using inference they only pay attention
to information that confirms their
belief they don't pay good attention
they don't find relevant enough the
information that could disconfirm their
belief they have what's called a
confirmation bias an active
open-mindedness you learn to become
aware and sensitive to confirmation bias
and
actively counteracted but that's not our
only form of knowing that's not our only
form of learning that's not the only
kind of pattern there's also right
knowing how to do something knowing how
to walk knowing how to catch a ball
knowing how to follow a conversation
knowing how to tell a joke these are not
matters of inference these are matters
of attention I have to pay attention in
the right way I have to track courses of
events I have to know how the rope this
isn't about propositions that express
beliefs this is about skills that enable
me to interact with the world well so
now I need a learning to learn strategy
for this procedural paying of attention
I have to train skills of attention I
have to have the practice of paying
attention to how I pay attention that's
exactly what mindfulness is so
mindfulness training is again this kind
of recursion
I learned to pay attention to how I'm
paying attention and in that way I can
improve my cognitive skills but there's
a third kind of knowing and I owe this
to my friend Gregor Soros there's a
perspectival knowing this is knowing
that something this is the case this is
knowing how to do something this is
knowing what it's like to be something
to take a particular role so Leo Ferrara
and I have done work trying to integrate
this all together and the idea is in
perspectival knowing I'm bringing
together my procedural know-how and my
propositional grasp of facts and I'm
integrating them together so that I know
what kind of role to take in a situation
I'm learning how to take perspectives
I'm learning how to assume roles but I
need that process also to be trained
there's a rationality for that well how
do we train our ability to take
perspectives why is that crucial to
rationality one of the bisetti things
that makes us irrational is a failure to
take alternative perspectives we are
often too egocentric in our processing
and what we need to do is overcome our
ego centrism
by taking broader and better
perspectives in our own learning how to
internalize them learning how to imitate
them that's a process that Vygotsky the
psychologists called internalization now
one of the things we can do
and this is one of the ideas that comes
from the ancient world and the study of
wisdom is we can set up this idea as the
child is to the adult the adult is to
the sage what children do in order to
become less egocentric is they practice
internalizing the perspective of adults
because that helps them to overcome
their bias their agha their ego centrism
it helps them to acquire skills and
interests they won't initially have from
their own egocentric force effective but
our development isn't done we can also
take that attitude of imitation and
internalization towards figures that
have better broader less biased
perspectives than ours so these are the
figures of course that are recognized by
history Jesus the Buddha Muhammad Lao si
kung fued say these are the sages we can
practice internalizing the sage as a way
of bringing rationality into our
perspective of knowing and then what we
can do is we can use these various forms
of rationality to act as checks and
balances on each other the procedural
right mindfulness the propositional
active open mindedness and the
perspectival internalizing the sage can
all interact with each other they can
all self correct and self transcendence
so what we can do is these various forms
of rationality can conform a
self-organizing system so that our
rationality is constantly
self-correcting constantly
self-transcending that's how wisdom
right can be the way rationality just
like an insight is a self-correcting
self-transcending process so what we get
with wisdom is that our rationality is
rationally transcending itself wisdom is
rationally self-transcending rationality
and wisdom matters because the more we
can free ourselves from the way the mind
is hampering itself the way the mind is
foolish the more we can afford
flourishing the war we can free our mind
to take on broader perspectives to
remove bias to be more insightful the
more we can bring to bear the cognitive
tools we need to improve our lives and
address some of the problems that are
facing the world the problems that need
more wisdom